The child's symptoms begin
تبدأ أعراض الطفل
with mild fever, headache, muscle pains,
بحمى خفيفة، صداع، الام في العضلات
followed by vomiting and diarrhea,
يتبعها قيئ و اسهال،
then bleeding from the mouth, nose and gums.
ثم نزيف من الفم و الأنف و اللثة.
Death follows in the form of organ failure from low blood pressure.
يتبع ذلك الموت بسبب فشل الأعضاء نتيجة لانخفاض ضغط الدم.
Sounds familiar?
يبدو ذلك مألوفا ؟
If you're thinking this is Ebola,
إذا كنت تعتقد أنها حالة إيبولا،
actually, in this case, it's not.
في الواقع، هذه الحالة، ليست كذلك.
It's an extreme form of dengue fever, a mosquito-born disease
انها شكل متطرف من حمى الضنك، مرض ينقل بواسطة البعوض
which also does not have an effective therapy or a vaccine,
و هو أيضا ليس له علاج فعال أو تطعيم،
and kills 22,000 people each year.
و يقتل 22000 شخص سنويا.
That is actually twice the number of people
هذا بالفعل ضعف عدد الناس
that have been killed by Ebola
الذين ماتوا بواسطة الإيبولا
in the nearly four decades that we've known about it.
في العقود الأربعة التي عرفناه فيها.
As for measles, so much in the news recently,
بالنسبة للحصبة- في الأخبار مؤخرا-
the death toll is actually tenfold higher.
تعداد الوفيات في الواقع أعلى بعشرة أضعاف.
Yet for the last year,
لكن في العام السابق،
it has been Ebola that has stolen all of the headlines and the fear.
فإن إيبولا هو الذي سرق كل العناوين و المخاوف.
Clearly, there is something deeply rooted about it,
بالطبع، هناك أمر
something which scares us and fascinates us
أمر يخيفنا و يبهرنا
more than other diseases.
أكثر من أي مرض آخر.
But what is it, exactly?
لكن ما هو بالضبط ؟
Well, it's hard to acquire Ebola,
حسنٌ، من الصعب الاصابة بإيبولا،
but if you do, the risk of a horrible death is high.
لكن إن حدث، فخطورة الموت البشع مرتفعة.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because right now, we don't have any effective therapy or vaccine available.
لأننا في الوقت الراهن، ليس لدينا أي علاج فعال أو تطعيم .
And so, that's the clue.
ولذلك فإن ما سبق ذكره هو الاجابة.
We may have it someday.
قد نحصل على العلاج أو اللقاح يوماً ما.
So we rightfully fear Ebola,
ولهذا نحن نخشى الأيبولا الآن
because it doesn't kill as many people as other diseases.
لأنه لا يقتل مثلما تفعل أمراضٌ أخرى.
In fact, it's much less transmissible than viruses such as flu or measles.
وفي الحقيقة إن فيروس الإيبولا أقل عدوىً من نظرائه من الفيروسات كالرشح أو الحصبة.
We fear Ebola because of the fact that it kills us and we can't treat it.
ونحن نخشى الأيبولا إنطلاقاً من قاعدة أنه يقتلنا ولا يمكننا علاجه.
We fear the certain inevitability that comes with Ebola.
نحن نخشى هذه الحتمية المُتعلقة بأيبولا.
Ebola has this inevitability that seems to defy modern medical science.
فأيبولا تتميز بهذه الحتمية والتي تبدو أنه تتحدى علم الطب الحديث.
But wait a second, why is that?
ولكن مهلاً, لماذا هذا؟
We've known about Ebola since 1976.
نحن قد عرفنا إيبولا منذ 1976 .
We've known what it's capable of.
وقد عرفنا ما هي حدود قدراته.
We've had ample opportunity to study it
وكان لدينا فرصة كافية لدراسته
in the 24 outbreaks that have occurred.
خلال ال24 مرة التي تفشى فيها
And in fact, we've actually had vaccine candidates available now
وفي الواقع, نحن نملك تطعيماً مرشحاً ومتاحاً
for more than a decade.
منذ أكثر من عقد.
Why is that those vaccines are just going into clinical trials now?
ولكن لماذا هذه اللقاحات تذهب للتجارب السريرية الآن؟
This goes to the fundamental problem we have
هذا يقودنا إلى المشكلة الرئيسية التي تواجهنا
with vaccine development for infectious diseases.
بشأن تطوير اللقاحات للأمراض المعدية.
It goes something like this:
وغالباً ما تجري الأمور على هذه الشاكلة:
The people most at risk for these diseases
الناس الأكثر عرضةً للإصابة بهذه الأمراض
are also the ones least able to pay for vaccines.
هم أيضاً الأقل قابلية على الدفع لقاء اللقاحات.
This leaves little in the way of market incentives
هذا يترك القليل في الطريق من الحوافز التسويقية
for manufacturers to develop vaccines,
للمُصنعين لأجل تطوير اللقاحات,
unless there are large numbers of people who are at risk in wealthy countries.
إلا إذا تواجدت أعداد ضخمة من الناس الذين هم في خطر في الدول الثرية.
It's simply too commercially risky.
وإنها ببساطة مخاطرة تجارية ضخمة.
As for Ebola, there is absolutely no market at all,
وبالنسبة لإيبولا فإنه لا يوجد للقاحات أي سوقٍ إطلاقاً,
so the only reason we have two vaccines in late-stage clinical trials now,
فالسبب الوحيد الذي يجعلنا نمتلك لقاحين في مرحلة متأخرة من التجارب السريرية,
is actually because of a somewhat misguided fear.
هو بسبب خوفٍ مُضَللٍ إلى حدٍ ما.
Ebola was relatively ignored
إيبولا تم تجاهلها نسبياً
until September 11 and the anthrax attacks,
حتى هجمات الجمرة الخبيثة في الحادي عشر من سبتمبر
when all of a sudden, people perceived Ebola
عندما تفاجئ الجميع بحجم الخطر الذي يمكن ان تسببه إيبولا
as, potentially, a bioterrorism weapon.
والتي يحتمل أن تكون أسلحةً كيميائيةً للإرهابيين.
Why is it that the Ebola vaccine wasn't fully developed at this point?
لماذا لم يتم تطوير لقاح إيبولا بشكل كامل في هذه المرحلة؟
Well, partially, because it was really difficult --
حقيقةً إن عملية التطوير كانت صعبة بشكلٍ جزئي
or thought to be difficult -- to weaponize the virus,
أو أنهم أعتقدوا أنه من الصعوبة بمكان استعمال الفايروس كسلاح
but mainly because of the financial risk in developing it.
ولكن بشكل رئيسي بسبب الخطر المالي المترتب على تطوير هكذا لقاح.
And this is really the point.
وهذه حقاً هي النقطة.
The sad reality is, we develop vaccines
والحقيقة المحزنة هي اننا نطور لقاحات
not based upon the risk the pathogen poses to people,
ليست مبنيةً على مسببات الأمراض التي يحتاجها الناس,
but on how economically risky it is to develop these vaccines.
وإنما على مدى المنفعة الاقتصادية لتطوير هكذا لقاحات.
Vaccine development is expensive and complicated.
إن تطوير اللقاحات هي عملية صعبة ومعقدة.
It can cost hundreds of millions of dollars
ويمكن أن تصل تكلفتها لمئات ملايين الدولارات
to take even a well-known antigen and turn it into a viable vaccine.
لأخذ مولدٍ مُضادٍ مشهورٍ وتحويله إلى لقاح.
Fortunately for diseases like Ebola,
ولحسن الحظ يمكننا القيام ببعض الامور لأمراض مثل الايبولا،
there are things we can do to remove some of these barriers.
لإزالة بعض ما يعيقنا في سبيل تصنيع اللقاح.
The first is to recognize when there's a complete market failure.
أول شيءٍ يجب ان نحدد إذا ما كان هناك فشل كامل في السوق لتأمين اللقاح.
In that case, if we want vaccines,
وفي هذه الحالة, إذا اردنا اللقاحات,
we have to provide incentives or some type of subsidy.
يجب علينا تأمين حوافزٍ أو بعض أنواع المعونات.
We also need to do a better job at being able to figure out
ويجب علينا القيام بعمل أفضل في سبيل تحديد
which are the diseases that most threaten us.
ما هي الأمراض الأكثر تهديداً لنا.
By creating capabilities within countries, we then create the ability
عبر خلق إمكانيات في داخل الدول ومن ثم خلق القدرة
for those countries to create epidemiological and laboratory networks
لهذه الدول على إنشاء شبكات الوبائية والمختبرية الخاصة.
which are capable of collecting and categorizing these pathogens.
والتي يجب أن تكون قادرة على تجميع وفرز مسببات الأمراض.
The data from that then can be used
إن البيانات من تلك الشبكات يمكن استعمالها
to understand the geographic and genetic diversity,
لفهم التنوعات الجينية والجغرافية,
which then can be used to help us understand
والتي يمكنها ان تساعدنا
how these are being changed immunologically,
على فهم التغيُرات المناعية
and what type of reactions they promote.
وما هي ردات الفعل التي تتطلبها.
So these are the things that can be done,
إن هذه أمور يمكن إنجازها,
but to do this, if we want to deal with a complete market failure,
ولكن إذا ما اردنا فعل هذا بالنظر إلى فشل كامل بالسوق الدوائية,
we have to change the way we view and prevent infectious diseases.
يجب علينا حينئذٍ تغيير طريقة عرضنا ومنعنا للأمراض المعدية.
We have to stop waiting until we see evidence
يجب علينا ان لا ننتظر حتى نرى الدليل,
of a disease becoming a global threat before we consider it as one.
على المرض هو تحوله لظاهرة عالمية .
So, for Ebola,
ولذا لأجل إيبولا,
the paranoid fear of an infectious disease,
الخوف المرضي من العدوى المرضيَّة,
followed by a few cases transported to wealthy countries,
متبوعةً بعدد من الحالات المنقولة إلى الدول الغنية,
led the global community to come together,
قادت المجتمع الدولي إلى الاجتماع,
and with the work of dedicated vaccine companies,
والعمل على تكريس شركات صناعة اللقاحات,
we now have these:
والآن هذه:
Two Ebola vaccines in efficacy trials in the Ebola countries --
لقاحان للإيبولا في حالة التجربة الفعلية في الدول المصابة بوباء الأيبولا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
and a pipeline of vaccines that are following behind.
وأنابيب من اللقاحات التي ستتبعها.
Every year, we spend billions of dollars,
كل عام نُنفق مليارات الدولارات,
keeping a fleet of nuclear submarines permanently patrolling the oceans
للإبقاء على اسطول الغواصات النووية يقوم بدوريات دائمة في المحيطات,
to protect us from a threat that almost certainly will never happen.
لحمايتنا من تهديدٍ بات معظمنا مقتنعاً بأنه لن يحدث أبداً.
And yet, we spend virtually nothing
ورغم هذا, إننا لم ننفق شيئاً يُذكر
to prevent something as tangible and evolutionarily certain
لمنع شيء محددٍ تطوريّاً وملموسٍ
as epidemic infectious diseases.
كالأوبية المَرضية المُعدية
And make no mistake about it -- it's not a question of "if," but "when."
وعلينا ألا نخطئ في ذلك. إنه سؤال "متى" لا "إذا".
These bugs are going to continue to evolve
إن هذه الثغرات ستستمر بالتطور
and they're going to threaten the world.
وهي تتشكل تهديداً حقيقياً للعالم.
And vaccines are our best defense.
واللقاحات هي أفضل سَبل الدفاع والوقاية.
So if we want to be able to prevent epidemics like Ebola,
ولذا إذا ما اردنا القضاء على الأوبئة مثل الأيبولا,
we need to take on the risk of investing in vaccine development
فإنه يتوجب علينا الاستثمار في قطاع تطوير اللقاحات
and in stockpile creation.
وإنشاء مخزون إحتياطي منها .
And we need to view this, then, as the ultimate deterrent --
ونحن بحاجة إلى إظهار هذا المخزون كرادع مطلق
something we make sure is available,
شيءٍ ييجب ان نتأكد من توافره ,
but at the same time, praying we never have to use it.
ولكن في نفس الوقت, يجب علينا أن ندعو الله ان لا نضطر لاستعماله
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)